<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homotopy theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/homotopy-theory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homotopy theory on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/homotopy-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sha Algebras</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/sha-algebras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/sha-algebras/</guid>
      <description>This is part four in a sort of connected story about operations in mathematics that are associative up to homotopy. It will probably be beneficial to read part 1, part 2 and part 3 in advance of this, but it is not required in theory. These previous posts do however build up some intuition and motivation for the object we are looking at today. To quickly recap what we already seen in these previous posts we recall that we started out by looking at how to transfer a group structure on a topological space through an isomorphism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Associative Algebraic Product</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-associating-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-associating-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>In the two last posts we have been discussing operations that are associative up to homotopy, and where such operations might arise naturally in topology. One claim I made, which I later realized was maybe a bit unmotivated and in need of some clarification was how some higher arity maps actually defined (or were defined by) homotopies between combinations of the lower arity maps. We also purely looked at this in a topological setting, but in algebraic topology we often translate to algebraic structures, so I also wanted to see clearly that the same constructions hold in that setting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Associativity</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-associativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-associativity/</guid>
      <description>Imagine we have a system of two topological spaces $f:T\longrightarrow G$. We are often interested in knowing if a certain property on the space $G$ can be transferred through f such that we have the same property on $T$. If f is a nice enough morphism an example could be a topological invariant of $G$, for example its Euler characteristic. In this post we are more interested in transferring other things than invariants, more specifically structures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quasi Categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/quasi-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/quasi-categories/</guid>
      <description>A couple weeks ago I held a talk on introductory higher category theory. Most of the talk was based upon thing we already have discussed on this blog, such as the strict $2$-category $Cat$, bicategories, and why strictness fails for the category of topological spaces. The inly thing I talked about which I haven’t yet featured on this blog is the notion of quasi-categories, so I though that I would do that today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Homotopy Litmus Test</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-litmus-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-litmus-test/</guid>
      <description>A litmus test is a question asked in politics to a potential candidate for high office in which the answer determines if the person gets nominated or not. If a person or a committee holds the power of nominating candidates, they can use that power to make sure that a potential candidate holds their view on a certain matter. So, what does this have to do with mathematics, or especially with homotopy theory?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The homotopy category</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-category/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-homotopy-category/</guid>
      <description>This is part 9 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 6, 7 and 8.
Last time we ended by giving a definition of a homotopy between maps on the collection of bifibrant objects in a model category. Today we are going to expand further upon this idea, and try to build the theory we are familiar with for topological spaces but in the general setting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy in model categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-in-model-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-in-model-categories/</guid>
      <description>This is part 8 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 6, 7 and 9.
Last time we finally defined the model category, gave some examples and tried (kind of) to give a motivation to why they are interesting and how they set the stage for homotopy theory. The first time I read the definition I was a bit confused about the lack of mention of homotopy, or at least some prototype of it that I could connect with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model categories</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/model-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/model-categories/</guid>
      <description>This is part 7 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 6, 8 and 9.
Finally we have made it to the destination we set, namely, more abstraction. This post is focused on the definition and intuition on model categories, which abstracts the objects we have been studying for some weeks, namely fibrations and cofibrations. The main definition is that of a model structure on a category, which together with a nice category will form the definition of a model category.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cofibrations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/cofibrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/cofibrations/</guid>
      <description>This is part 6 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 7, 8 and 9.
Through the series so far we have covered the basic uses of fibrations and related things, like the long exact sequence of homotopy groups, the Serre spectral sequence, fiber bundles and homotopy groups of spheres. But, we have not mentioned that fibrations has a dual construct, namely cofibrations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hanging Pictures With Homotopy</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/hanging-pictures-with-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/hanging-pictures-with-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago I saw this problem of hanging a picture on the wall using a string and two nails in such a way that if you remove one of the nails from the wall, the picture falls down. This is a bad way to hang pictures you immediately say, and I would agree. I saw some solution to the problem, and didn’t think about it for many years, until this week when I figured out that we need homotopy, in particular the fundamental group, to do it!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A homotopy group of a sphere</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/a-homotopy-group-of-a-sphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/a-homotopy-group-of-a-sphere/</guid>
      <description>This is part 5 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8 and 9.
As promised in the previous part, we are going to calculate $\pi_4(S^3)$. I think we will have to use all of the machinery (plus some new) that we have been through during this series to do the calculation. What more could we possibly need you ask?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Serre spectral sequence</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</guid>
      <description>This is part 4 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
My personal favorite part about fibrations is that they come equipped with a natural way to compute the cohomology of the total space from the cohomology of the base and the cohomology of the fibers. This process is encoded in a structure called a spectral sequence, and is a complicated object in its full generality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy groups</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</guid>
      <description>This is part 3 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 4, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
For an introduction to the material, the definitions, motivation and some examples, please read part 1 and part 2 about fibrations and fiber bundles. This and the the following parts of this series will be about their usefulness, especially in computing homology and homotopy groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fiber bundles</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fiber-bundles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fiber-bundles/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 3, 4, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
Yesterday we discussed the standard definition of a fibration by the homotopy lifting property, and today we are continuing that discussion, but in a more visual manner. This we will do by first looking at fiber bundles, and then generalizing them. Since fibrations are generalized fiber bundles, every fiber bundle is an example of a fibration, and they have been the most important examples for me, as they help me visualize and get intuition into the fibrations without having to really use the full generality of the definition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fibrations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fibrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fibrations/</guid>
      <description>This is part 1 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 2, 3, 4, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
My main mathematical interest for the last couple years has been algebraic topology. I feel it suits my needs for intuition, and graphical picturing of what happens. A concept I have been learning more rigorously recently is fibrations, and how to use them in computing homotopy groups and homology groups of different spaces.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
