<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Noether normalization on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/tags/noether-normalization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Noether normalization on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/tags/noether-normalization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Updated geometric intuition</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/updated-geometric-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/updated-geometric-intuition/</guid>
      <description>The first post on this blog is titled &amp;ldquo;geometric intuition&amp;rdquo;, and discusses the geometry behind Noether&amp;rsquo;s normalization lemma. When I wrote it I didn&amp;rsquo;t yet understand all the pieces, as I was not very comfortable working with algebraic geometry. One year later, I&amp;rsquo;m still not comfortable, but a bit more than last year. So, I thought I would update last years post with my new knowledge, as well as generalize the intuition to schemes - which we introduced in the last post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Intuition</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/geometric-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/geometric-intuition/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This spring I have been taking a graduate class in commutative algebra, and I have yet to do algebraic geometry in a proper way, and have only gotten a small taste while writing my bachelor thesis. So this entire semester, I have felt this hinting at a geometric picture from the algebra itself, but i didn&amp;rsquo;t have the insight to figure it out. That said, I now think I have the geometric picture for Noether normalization, which in term implies a geometric picture of Hilbert nullstellensatz and some other results.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
