<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Algebraic topology on Writing what I&#39;m learning</title>
    <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/algebraic-topology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Algebraic topology on Writing what I&#39;m learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright> </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/categories/algebraic-topology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Associative Algebraic Product</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-associating-homotopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/the-associating-homotopy/</guid>
      <description>In the two last posts we have been discussing operations that are associative up to homotopy, and where such operations might arise naturally in topology. One claim I made, which I later realized was maybe a bit unmotivated and in need of some clarification was how some higher arity maps actually defined (or were defined by) homotopies between combinations of the lower arity maps. We also purely looked at this in a topological setting, but in algebraic topology we often translate to algebraic structures, so I also wanted to see clearly that the same constructions hold in that setting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spaces With Operations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/spaces-with-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/spaces-with-operations/</guid>
      <description>In the most recent blog post we discussed homotopy associativity and how to transfer algebraic structures on topological spaces. There we in particular used topological groups, which are topological spaces with group structures. That said, any group is a topological group by equipping it with the discrete topology. So if we want to study some actual topology, and not just glorified group theory, we need to look at where multiplications and binary operations arise naturally in topology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Associativity</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-associativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/homotopy-associativity/</guid>
      <description>Imagine we have a system of two topological spaces $f:T\longrightarrow G$. We are often interested in knowing if a certain property on the space $G$ can be transferred through f such that we have the same property on $T$. If f is a nice enough morphism an example could be a topological invariant of $G$, for example its Euler characteristic. In this post we are more interested in transferring other things than invariants, more specifically structures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hanging Pictures With Knots</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/hanging-pictures-with-knots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2021/hanging-pictures-with-knots/</guid>
      <description>Last year I posted a blog post where we looked at a way to use elementary homotopy theory to hang a picture on the wall in a stupid way. The task was to hang a picture on two nails in such a way that if we pull one of the nails out, the picture falls down. “That is stupid” I hear you say, but premise is as premise does, or something similar quoted from Forrest Gump.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are There Knots?</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/there-are-knots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/there-are-knots/</guid>
      <description>Something I have been looking into a bit lately, due to it sadly not being taught at my university is knot theory. This is something I have always known to be a part of topology, and have known to have interesting applications in physics, medicine, chemistry and more. So to rectify the situation I thought I would prove that knots exist. It was also nice to take a brake from all the higher category theory we have been looking into lately!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Warsaw Circle</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-warsaw-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-warsaw-circle/</guid>
      <description>The last few posts have all been of relatively long length and have all taken some time to construct and write. I initially also wanted to produce shorter posts just discussing an example or a calculation etc, and today I tried to do just that, but failed. The post became somewhat longer than intended, but it is really informal and intuitive, so its fine in my opinion.
In a previous post we discussed both weak homotopy equivalences and regular homotopy equivalences, and we have also encountered the Whitehead theorem, which says that any weak homotopy equivalence between CW-complexes is in fact a regular homotopy equivalence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/orbifolds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/orbifolds/</guid>
      <description>For quite some time I have occasionally stumbled onto the Wikipedia page for orbifolds while looking at topology related mathematics. I have always been fascinated by them, and always though that they certainly will come up during studies at university, but they never have (at least not yet). On said wikipedia page it says that the word orbifold is short for “orbit manifold” and that these orbifolds are in fact a generalization of manifolds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swans Theorem</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/swans-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/swans-theorem/</guid>
      <description>A part of mathematics I really an starting to enjoy more is mathematics that explain or develop connections between geometry or topology, and algebra. The first two posts on this blog was focused on developing some geometrical insight to two lemmas from commutative algebra, namely Noether’s normalization lemma and Zariski’s lemma. There are many more such connections worth discussing and exploring, and today I want to focus on one of these “bridges” between geometry and algebra, namely Swan’s theorem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cofibrations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/cofibrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/cofibrations/</guid>
      <description>This is part 6 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 7, 8 and 9.
Through the series so far we have covered the basic uses of fibrations and related things, like the long exact sequence of homotopy groups, the Serre spectral sequence, fiber bundles and homotopy groups of spheres. But, we have not mentioned that fibrations has a dual construct, namely cofibrations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A homotopy group of a sphere</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/a-homotopy-group-of-a-sphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/a-homotopy-group-of-a-sphere/</guid>
      <description>This is part 5 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8 and 9.
As promised in the previous part, we are going to calculate $\pi_4(S^3)$. I think we will have to use all of the machinery (plus some new) that we have been through during this series to do the calculation. What more could we possibly need you ask?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Serre spectral sequence</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/the-serre-spectral-sequence/</guid>
      <description>This is part 4 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 3, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
My personal favorite part about fibrations is that they come equipped with a natural way to compute the cohomology of the total space from the cohomology of the base and the cohomology of the fibers. This process is encoded in a structure called a spectral sequence, and is a complicated object in its full generality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy groups</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/homotopy-groups/</guid>
      <description>This is part 3 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 2, 4, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
For an introduction to the material, the definitions, motivation and some examples, please read part 1 and part 2 about fibrations and fiber bundles. This and the the following parts of this series will be about their usefulness, especially in computing homology and homotopy groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fiber bundles</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fiber-bundles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fiber-bundles/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 1, 3, 4, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
Yesterday we discussed the standard definition of a fibration by the homotopy lifting property, and today we are continuing that discussion, but in a more visual manner. This we will do by first looking at fiber bundles, and then generalizing them. Since fibrations are generalized fiber bundles, every fiber bundle is an example of a fibration, and they have been the most important examples for me, as they help me visualize and get intuition into the fibrations without having to really use the full generality of the definition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fibrations</title>
      <link>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fibrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://torgeiraamboe.github.io/posts/2020/fibrations/</guid>
      <description>This is part 1 of a series leading up to and exploring model categories. For the other parts see 2, 3, 4, 5 6, 7, 8 and 9.
My main mathematical interest for the last couple years has been algebraic topology. I feel it suits my needs for intuition, and graphical picturing of what happens. A concept I have been learning more rigorously recently is fibrations, and how to use them in computing homotopy groups and homology groups of different spaces.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
